Pablo Badilla Torrealba

Machine Learning Engineer

pbadilla.torrealba@gmail.com



+56971396025



Github



Linkedin

ABOUT

Engineer with 5+ years of experience in development and productization of systems based on Data Science, Machine Learning (ML) and Natural Language Processing (NLP) in various sectors, including retail, banking, software and research. Strong communication and project management skills.

EXPERIENCE

WALMART CHILE | Senior Machine Learning Engineer

Mavo 2023 - Mavo 2024

- → Development and deploy of a call center demand forecasting model.
- → Development and deploy of a customer lifetime value model (CLTV).
- → Reimplementation and deployment of an MM1/MMS queuing simulation model that ran daily on all supermarket checkouts.

BCI | DATA SCIENTIST

February 2023 - April 2023

→ Development of features based on banking transactions for credit risk assessment models.

NATIONAL ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER OF CHILE (CENIA)

MACHINE LEARNING ENGINEER

Enero 2022 - Enero 2023

→ Development and deployment of Machine Learning model to incorporate user preferences in Vehicle Routing Problem (VRP).

KWIYX SPA - FREELANCE | DESARROLLADOR FULL STACK & DATA SCIENTIST

March 2019 - January 2021

- → Front-end development of real estate investment app.
- → Full-stack development of an application for human resources management in pandemic hospitals based on optimization models.
- → Automated topic and argument detection using embeddings generated by Transformers embeddings.
- → IOU text detection system with OCR and Regex.

UNIVERSITY OF CHILE | PART TIME LECTURER

Marzo 2021 - Julio 2023

→ Scientific Programming Laboratory for Data Science lecture, for the Master in Data Science.

PROJECTS

DASHAI | SOFTWARE ARCHITECT & SENIOR DEVELOPER

→ Interactive library to train, evaluate and deploy Al models, currently under development. Link to DashAl in Github.

WEFE | MAIN DEVELOPER

→ Open-source library for bias assesment in Word Embeddings models. Link to WEFF in Github and to Read the Docs.

Tools

Programming Languages

- Proficient Python
- Intermediate JavaScript

Data Science

- Numpy Pandas SQL BigQuery
- Spark JupyterLab/Databricks Plotly
- NLTK

Machine Learning

- Scikit-learn XGBoost LightGBM
- Pytorch HuggingFace

Tools and platforms

- GCP / Vertex AI Git Github Actions
- Docker Kubeflow Kedro Sphinx
- FastAPI ChatGPT, Gemini, Copilot.

Methodologies and best practices

• MLOps • CI/CD • Pull Requests & Code Review • Code documentation, testing, linting & formatting • Kanban & Scrum

EDUCATION

MASTER'S DEGREE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

University of Chile 2019-2020

BACHELOR OF COMPUTER SCIENCE

University of Chile 2013-2019

LANGUAGES

- Spanish Native speaker
- English (B2 TOEFL-ITP)

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Bachelor's and Master's degree graduate with highest distinction.
- #93 Top GitHub Users By Public Contributions in Chile
- Academic Advisor in University of Chile.
- 2 times outstanding student in University of Chile.